Irene Balelli

Ph.D.

Inria Sophia Antipolis, Epione Team 2004 Route des Lucioles. 06902 Valbonne, France © 0033 602082747 ⊠ irene.balelli@inria.fr irenebalelli.wix.com/site



Biographical Information

November 3, 1988, in Forlimpopoli - Italy.

Citizenship Italian.

Marital status Under PACS.

Family Two children (2015 and 2018).

situation

Research Interests

Machine Federated learning. Distributed learning. Bayesian Statistics. Data mining. Latent variable models.

Generative models. Large-scale heterogeneous secured biomedical data. Learning

Modeling/ Identifiability analysis. Sensitivity analysis. Parameter estimation with population approach. Mixed

Statistics effects models. Expectation Maximization

Biomedical Neurodegenerative diseases: Alzheimer Disease. Parkinson Disease. Imaging data.

Applications Immunology: Immune response dynamics. Immune system. Antibody affinity maturation. B-cells.

Immune memory. Vaccination.

Applied Random walks on graphs. Markov chains. Graph theory. Galton-Watson processes. Evolutionary

Probability landscapes

Current Position

2021-now Research scientist (ISFP) in mathematical modeling for computational biomedicine, EPI-

ONE team - Centre Inria d'Université Côte d'Azur, Valbonne - France.

Experience

2020-2021 Post-doctoral research fellowship in federated statistical learning for new generation metaanalyses of large-scale and secured biomedical data, EPIONE team - Inria Sophia Antipolis

Méditerranée, Valbonne - France.

2017-2019 Post-doctoral research fellowship in modeling of the immune response to Ebola vaccine,

SISTM team - Inserm U1219 Bordeaux Population Health, Bordeaux - France.

Education

2013–2016 PhD in Applied Mathematics with teaching activities, LAGA - Université Paris 13, Villetaneuse

Title: Mathematical foundations of antibody affinity maturation.

Supervisors: Vuk Milišić, Gilles Wainrib, Hatem Zaag.

Defense date: November 30, 2016.

2011-2013 Master Degree in Mathematics Applied to Biology and Medicine, Master thesis: A mathe-

matical model of somatic hypermutation (Supervisors: V. Milišić, G. Wainrib), Université Paris 6,

2010-2011 Erasmus Program, Universidad Complutense, Department of Mathematics, Madrid - Spain.

2007–2010 **Bachelor degree in Mathematics**, *Bachelor thesis:* Il modello di Bressloff e Cowan: allucinazioni visive come stati stabili di attivazione corticale (*Supervisor: G. Citti*), Universitá di Bologna, Bologna - Italy.

Papers and Preprints

- **I. Balelli**, S. Silva, M. Lorenzi., A Differentially Private Probabilistic Framework for Federated Heterogeneous Multi-View Datasets Variability, Submitted to Journal of Machine Learning for Biomedical Imaging (MELBA).
- **I. Balelli**, S. Silva, M. Lorenzi., *A Probabilistic Framework for Modeling the Variability Across Federated Datasets of Heterogeneous Multi-View Observations*, International Conference on Information Processing in Medical Imaging. Springer, Cham, 2021. p. 701-714.
- Q. Clairon, C. Pasin, I. Balelli, R. Thiébaut, M. Prague., *Parameter estimation in nonlinear mixed effect models based on ordinary differential equations: an optimal control approach*, [arXiv: 2102.11543].
- M. Prague, J. Gerold, **I. Balelli**, C. Pasin, J. Li, D. Barouch, J. Whitney, A. Hill., *Viral rebound kinetics following single and combination immunotherapy for HIV/SIV*, [bioRxiv 700401; doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/700401].
- **I. Balelli**, C. Pasin, M. Prague, F. Crauste, T. Van Effelterre, V. Bockstal, L. Solforosi, R. Thiébaut, *A model for establishment, maintenance and reactivation of the immune response after vaccination against Ebola virus*, Journal of Theoretical Biology, 2020, DOI: 10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110254.
- C. Pasin, **I. Balelli**, T. Van Effelterre, V. Bockstal, L. Solforosi, M. Prague, M. Douoguih, R. Thiébaut, *Dynamics of the humoral immune response to a prime-boost Ebola vaccine: quantification and sources of variation*, Journal of Virology, 2019, **DOI:** 10.1128/JVI.00579-19.
- **I.** Balelli, V. Milišić, G. Wainrib, *Multi-type Galton-Watson processes with affinity-dependent selection applied to antibody affinity maturation*, Bulletin of Mathematical Biology, 2019, vol. 81, no 3, p. 830-868.
- **I. Balelli**, V. Milišić, G. Wainrib, *Random walks on binary strings applied to the somatic hypermutation of B-cells*, Mathematical Biosciences, 2018, vol. 300, p. 168-186.
- **I. Balelli**, V. Milišić, G. Wainrib, *Branching random walks on binary strings for evolutionary processes in adaptive immunity*, [arXiv: 1607.00927].

Attended Conferences, Meetings and Seminars

- 2021 Information Processing in Medical Imaging (IPMI) 2021, Poster, Online event.
- 2020 3IA Scientific Days, Poster, Nice France.
 - Sophl.A Summit 2020, Talk, Sophia Antipolis France.
- 2019 $4^{\hat{t}h}$ EBOVAC1/2 Annual meeting, Talk, Nairobi Kenya.
 - VRI Annual meeting, Talk, Paris France.
- 2018 IMI 10^{th} Anniversary Scientific Symposium, Talk, 3^{rd} committee prize "best presentation", Brussels Belgium.
 - **CROI 2018**, Poster (J.M. Gerold, C. Pasin, I. Balelli, S. Lim, C. Osuna, J.B. Whitney, D.H. Barouch, M. Prague, A.L. Hill), Boston United States.
 - 3rd EBOVAC1/2 Annual meeting, Talk (shared with C. Pasin), Amsterdam Nederland.
- 2017 Systems Immunology and Vaccine design, Heidelberg Germany.
- 2016 Probabilities and Statistics seminar (LAGA), Talk, Villetaneuse France.
 - 1st Challenges in inflammation meeting, Florence Italy.
 - Les probabilités de demain, Talk, IHÉS Bures-sur-Yvette France.
 - Summer school: "PDE and Probability for Life Sciences", Poster, CIRM Marseille France.
- 2015 EDP-Normandie, Poster, Havre France.
- 2014 InflaConf: Mathematical modeling in immunology and inflammation, Talk, Paris France.

CANUM 2014, Poster, Carry-le-Rouet - France.

Inflamex day, Talk, CIEP Sèvres - France.

2013 GDR Métice: Inflammation and Treatment Resistance, Talk, Lyon - France.

Thematic schools

2021 **Al4Health Winter School**, *Workshop:* Handling heterogeneity in the analysis of biomedical information, Online event.

First Inria-DFKI European Summer School on Artificial Intelligence, *Workshop:* Federated learning methods and frameworks for collaborative data analysis, Online event.

Teaching Activities

2020-2021 **Bayesian learning**, *Lectures and tutorials*, M2 MSc Data Science & Artificial Intelligence, University Côte d'Azur.

Sophia Antipolis - France

Modeling of biological systems, *Lectures and tutorials*, M2 BIM, University Côte d'Azur. Nice - France

2013-2016 **Probability and Statistics 2**, *Tutorials*, 2nd year bachelor's degree in Mathematics and MIEF, University Paris 13.

Villetaneuse - France

Probability and Statistics 1, *Tutorials*, 2nd year bachelor's degree in Mathematics, University Paris 13.

Villetaneuse - France

Probability and Statistics, *Tutorials*, 1st year Engineering degree (Apprentissage énergétique), Engineering School Sup Galilée.

Villetaneuse - France

Statistics, *Tutorials*, 1st year Engineering degree MACS (Mathématiques Appliquées et Calcul Scientifique), Engineering School Sup Galilée.

Villetaneuse - France

Probability, Tutorials, 2nd year IUT-Info, University Paris 13.

Villetaneuse - France

Inferential statistics, Tutorials, 2nd year DUT-GEA, University Paris 13.

Bobigny - France

References

Marco Lorenzi marco.lorenzi@inria.fr Hatem Zaag zaag@math.univ-paris13.fr
Rodolphe rodolphe.thiebaut@u-bordeaux.fr Vuk Milišić milisic@math.univ-paris13.fr
Thiébaut Gilles Wainrib gilles.wainrib@owkin.com

Computer Skills

Programming Python, Matlab, R Operating Mac 0SX, Linux, Windows

Languages Systems

Parameter Monolix, NIMROD Numerical Stochastic processes, Monte Carlo estimation Simulations methods, ODE system (simulation /

softwares sensitivity analysis)

Editing & OpenOffice, Office, Later Others Identifiability Analysis (Mathemat-

Office ica), DAISY (Reduce3.8)

Languages

Italian Mother tongue English Fluent